<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Transcript of an Interview with Kenneth Marable</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <orgName>Dartmouth Black Lives</orgName>
        </authority>
        <date>
          <!--  Date of publication, e.g. for citation purposes  -->
        </date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <recordingStmt>
          <recording xml:id="primary_recording" type="audio" dur-iso="00:00:00">
            <!-- https://www.digi.com/resources/documentation/digidocs/90001437-13/reference/r_iso_8601_duration_format.htm -->
            <media url="" mimeType="video/mp4"/>
          </recording>
        </recordingStmt>
        <bibl xml:id="primary_transcription">
          <respStmt>
            <persName>Jeremy Romano</persName>
            <orgName>Dartmouth Black Lives</orgName>
            <resp ref="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/trc.html">Transcriber</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <ref target="path_to_file">Primary transcription</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Dartmouth Black Lives</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="DDHIEncoder" version="1.0">
          <desc>Conversion from Word docx to TEI xml.</desc>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-us">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <person xml:id="MARABLE"/>
        <person xml:id="Marable"/>
        <person xml:id="ROMANO"/>
      </particDesc>
      <settingDesc>
        <setting>
          <date when-iso="2022-10-23"/>
          <locale/>
        </setting>
      </settingDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u who="ROMANO">So let me first start. I am <persName>Jeremy Romano</persName>, I am currently in <placeName>Blunt, Alumni Hall</placeName> in front of <placeName>Sanborn Hall</placeName> and I am interviewing for the <orgName>Dartmouth Oral History Project</orgName>. <orgName>Dartmouth Black lives</orgName>. I have the pleasure to be with <persName>Kenneth Marable</persName> ['74] and yeah, it's a great pleasure meeting you Mr. <persName>Marable</persName>. How are you doing today?</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">I'm doing good. It's good meeting you even though our schedules.  It Has been very, very tight being you studying in the stacks and I've been running around doing what I do here in <placeName>New York City</placeName>, but we finally have an opportunity to talk and meet each other visually. </u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Yeah, yes just to make sure to retain the date. Today is <date when='2022-10-23'>October 23, 2022</date>, and we do an online interview, and I am currently in <placeName>Hanover, New Hampshire</placeName> and you are currently in <placeName>New York</placeName>. Is that right?</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">That's right. I'm in <placeName>Brooklyn, New York</placeName>, the center of the universe.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Yeah, So let me just start with just the most basic things. Could you please just tell me a little bit about your childhood and your upbringing in the early years of your life? And can you please state what State you were born, in and what date you were born?</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">Okay. I will forget something, please let me know. So I was born on <date when='1952-01-31'>January 31st, 1952</date>, I was born in <placeName>Bronxville Hospital</placeName>, which was the closest hospital to the village that I grew up in, in <placeName>Westchester County</placeName> [New York]. I grew up In a village called <placeName>Tuckahoe</placeName>, this little town. So <placeName>Tuckahoe</placeName> was as I defined it a location that was between two relatively wealthy areas, <placeName>Bronxville</placeName> in <placeName>Scarsdale</placeName>, and we provided sort of the service work for those individuals. In those locations, my mother [Odessa Marable] had a seamstress shop. She was self-employed. And she basically was a dressmaker and my father [Joseph Marable], who was also self-employed, was a house painter. And so between the two of them thinking about it. That's, that's where I guess. I had a really good close-up front picture of family life, where two parents are working as entrepreneurs, and struggling. Yeah, well maybe I didn't think it was struggling but working very hard to provide for their families. So <placeName>Tuckahoe</placeName> had essentially two schools. The elementary school was. That is where I did my kindergarten. Yeah. To sixth grade and <placeName>Tuckahoe</placeName> was a small enough location that effectively walked to school, and my high school years took place in <placeName>Tuckahoe High school</placeName>. So, I guess, because my parents work hard to be able to live in a house, they purchased their own house after several years of living, in my grandfather's house. and <placeName>Tuckahoe</placeName> had interesting demographics. In this sense that you were Black, Leaving one part of town. projects. You had Italian, and Italians living in a different part of town and I defined them as upcoming Black living in another part of town. My Parents moved into that area and had a house on the hill. and then you had a different part of town that was wealthy Black. So it was, it was sort of integrated, but segmented in a way that you have it attached. Add the middle-class Blacks over here and you had the poor Blacks over there. When I was a paperboy. I remember going to deliver papers to someone who has a wood-burning stove. And so you have to imagine a wood-burning stove with all the smoke as you're getting the fire. Those are some interesting memories. So I went to <placeName>Tuckahoe High School</placeName> and that school had about 600 students. That was grades 7 through 12. To. It was a very small school and it was a collection of Italians and Jews blacks. The school was, I would say, an integrated school. So my growing up experience was really dealing with all kinds of people and really at least, I was not having any racial tension. Nothing. That would. Be of concern, at least not to me. And so, during my high school years, I was the president of the student government and the football captain for a couple of years. Running back defensive player, our Squad was so so small we called ourselves the dirty does because that's all we had. We had 12 players. So we went both ways, the left side of the offense, Played the right side of the defense and we had the coaches suit up also. So we could play. I think we won one game and were out of an 87 Game season. And then, the next year, we basically won the title for the <orgName>Westchester County football conference</orgName>, and I think it was during that year, I remember one of my best football games where I ran 400 yards during the game for a touchdown. So I was the football hero.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Great. So you mentioned just a lot of pressures crashing. When it is your time around like junior-senior year of high school, do you already have the plan to go to college? Or were you thinking about other professions like a trade school or you just like you had your mindset set for college? Why did you choose <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> out of other colleges? especially from your football background? Very athletic. Please mention that.</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">I would say that Somewhere in the back of my mind. Both my parents did not go to college and they were entrepreneurs and workers, right so they Did their own thing. I don't I can't say that I had an intention, a focused intention of going to college, but in the back of my mind, I guess that's where I was directed. So, the high school had different classes. There was that sort of College material in those that were just regular. I'll say.  I was attracted to  More specialized classes to focus on college. So, The guidance counselor focused on college, and then it was discussed with me. I'm going to say it really wasn't all that helpful, at least not that I remember. I  look at colleges. You think you want to go to and so when I started thinking seriously about college and looking at where I would go I was actually thinking about <orgName>Northeastern</orgName> because they had this Program that was sort of a working and school program six-year program which was very interesting initially. The reason why I ended up at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was a random reason. I was president of the student government and the president before me. <persName>Steve Herzfeld</persName> went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. And then the president before him, <persName>Rob Melnick</persName>, went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. And they, you know, they told me about <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and you know,  good school, you need to think about that, didn't know anything about <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, didn't know, really anything about <orgName>ivy league</orgName>? And so because those two guys went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> I applied when the opportunity presented itself. the primary reason I guess the opportunity presented himself was because of the students that were in the earlier classes whose direct impact on increasing the number of Black students that were attending, you know, <persName>Ron tally</persName> [Ron Talley '69], walls <persName>Ford [Wally Ford '70]</persName>, some of these guys that, you know, Stood strong to ensure that the numbers of Black students attending increased. and so I think as a result of their efforts and the need for the college to increase the level of Black students there. And the three former student government presidents. Now, both of these guys were Jewish, guys. So you know, they said you need to go to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. I had no idea how much money was involved. Had no idea. If anything I applied because of the brothers at <orgName>Dartmouth Admission</orgName> said, well we have this candidate here, <persName>Ken Marable</persName>. Yeah, they were looking at my grades. and I was not a top, stellar student, but for whatever reason, they decided to admit me and it's so it is a combination of different random factors that resulted in me applying and getting accepted. </u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Yeah, thanks for that background and for sharing your mindset at that time. So you apply, you're going to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> and you are getting ready. You arrived in the fall of <date when='1970'>1970</date>, Am I right here, right? Right. Yeah, then your arrival for the <date when='1970'>1970</date> post-Civil Rights Movement era. there were still a lot of new African-Americans. As you mentioned the number of African-Americans increased on campus. So you arrive, you see yourself there can you walk me through, how was your Freshman fall. What was like, some of the stresses. Some experiences that you weren't expecting? Or it was just the easiest fall for freshman year. And could you tell me, do you have any connection to any Black upperclassmen before you enter campus organizations or You started a relationship with them once you were on campus?</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">So, I'm going to answer you as best I can. So the history that I tried to reflect growing up in <placeName>Tuckahoe</placeName>. Was one that gave me the ability to think and navigate reasonably well at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. So <placeName>Tuckahoe</placeName> is a little town right between Rich, wealthy, <placeName>Bronxville</placeName>, and  Rich, wealthy <placeName>Scarsdale</placeName>. I was in the advanced class and I might have been the only one Black in it. So I'm president of the student government. So my ability to navigate the different people and different types of demographics was okay, you know, I was not aware of Communicating with Black folk or white folk. And so, prior to becoming a freshman, I went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> to see the campus, and spend a little bit of time with <persName>Ted, [ Ted Thompson’ 66 ]</persName> and his brother who was cool. You know, I intentionally decided to go to a school that had no females with the thought that That's exactly what I need. Keep my mind occupied with studies and nothing else. I went around and saw, you know, I mean, the campus was mostly White there were few Black people, But I grew up in an environment like that and so, you know, nothing, nothing, new, nothing new. And so I decided, Well, good school, excellent opportunity. If they accept me then I know I can do what's necessary to graduate. My experience when I got there I moved to <placeName>North Massachusetts Hall</placeName>. It was a 2 room triple and I was in a  house with two white guys, and we learned to basically live together. They came from different academic levels. I went to public school. And if I am not mistaken, they went to private school or, you know, one public school that was very focused on academics. Both turned out to be doctors and recently one of my roommates passed away that was Carl [‘74] but Matt [74] and I still retain a good friendship and actually we were members of the class officers committee together. So my study habits were a little bit different than theirs but we live to learn to live together because I think I had to study a lot harder than most. Maybe I didn't, maybe I was doing what everybody else was doing, but I had the corner in the library over there. Then I found another place in the stacks.  so I thought because I was the football star in <placeName>Tuckahoe</placeName>, I could, you know, show what I could do on the <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> team. And so, I walked on, I was a walk-on. And, you know, I was used to running tailback but I guess because of my size they put me in the spot of fullback and because I hadn't actually been recruited. Yeah, I found my way on the bench and so, but the freshman team was good. I was part of the <date when='1972'>1972</date> Championship group. but a lot of what I remember was playing football and trying wrestling for a little bit. And then study, you know, Going to classes and studying.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Great. There's actually a little connection to me because I did try to walk on in the football team here. </u>
      <u who="MARABLE">Yeah well</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">It is a really big team right now. It's like so many guys,</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">There were so many guys but I was good. I was a good man and if I had stayed on the team, I would have probably played a lot, a lot more than I did. You know. So I did that during my freshman year and sophomore year, and I was on the team. And then junior year I said you know I need to make sure I do what I need to do and I devote more time to studies so I let it go of my junior year.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Nice. Thanks for sharing that. You major in economics and psychology. No no. You major in economics and you minor in psychology. That's right. Could you tell me a little bit about what you mentioned about trying to focus a lot on your academics, you'll find little spaces. Could you tell me about how you came to the conclusion of choosing that path of studying that major and minor? Tell me were there any specific people in the apartment that influenced your decision, or did you just feel like that is the right way? Because there are so many mayors in <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. So tell me a little bit about your mindset.</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">Then I probably didn't use all the resources that were available. I  wasn't part of the <orgName>ABC</orgName> program. I didn't, you know, come in early. I came in and maybe because I came from <placeName>Westchester County</placeName>, the level of academic and study skills were presumed to be available to me and they probably Were, but I don't know if anyone thought that this, this Black guy really needed them, but it wasn't the case. The most impactful teacher was my English teacher. I want to say her name was <persName>Professor King</persName>. I forget the name, but the biggest one of the challenges I had when I started was being able to write in a way that was In accordance with the way people write. Not necessarily the way people talk, right? So King helped me navigate English as far as economics and psychology. I knew I wanted to go into business, had no idea what business I was going to go into, didn't want to be a painter, and didn't feel like being a dressmaker but my parents were and I think about it now. And so the idea was to combine economics which as far as I was concerned, was the language of understanding, the business of pricing trends of supply and demand of understanding, how, how all of the intertwining aspects of Supply and demand of people's needs could make someone Successful. In psychology, I said well if I can get into people's minds and understand the psychology of people’s minds. Then that would be a good combination. So that is the reason why I did the economics major.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Nice I am actually an econ major I think it's really helpful actually..</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">Did you take economics 26? The money in banking course.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">I still haven't taken it. 26. No.</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">Do the labor. Cars course. Okay, I think it was economics 22, I believe. </u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Yeah, yeah, yeah. And I am still in the process of turning  21 right now. So definitely going to take 22. So</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">21 that's money in banking?</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">21 is microeconomics. Yeah, they change the numbers a little bit. Yeah, so thanks for that actually. I want to focus a little bit on like freshmen going to Winter. How was the weather? Surprise you at all? </u>
      <u who="MARABLE">Okay, so, you know, I live in <placeName>New York</placeName>. Yeah. Well, snow was used to the Four Seasons. I think the most impactful visual was the fall in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>, and if you sit in the stadium and look out in the distance, you can see all the trees in the color, so that was pretty interesting. I think the first winter was different because it was When you went outside, it was pretty cool. Very cool. And I don't think I've ever seen moisture crystallized. And so, if you can imagine, you're one of those movies, you're walking around and you're in heaven and you see these things floating around. It was a moisture-reflecting crystallized reflection in the sunlight. It was so cold. The hair in your nostrils was freezing. It's so cold. It was, it was cold over the years. It didn't get as cold looking at it now. </u>
      <u who="ROMANO">I agree. Something I wanted to ask you about the <date when='1970'>1970</date>  Faculty Now, do you recall any specific professors or tutors that were Black?  specifically, the diversity of different races within the faculty. Because <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> is still trying to diversify, not only the student body but also the faculty. So do you have any memory of it?</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">So I guess because of where I came from. High School. Yeah. Connected to the Black community differently. I think that some of the brothers had very little or no exposure to white people, you know. Yeah. And so some of the things that when people hate, they know who to connect to. I wasn't in that group to connect with them so I'm not going to say I was solo but T.A’s no, tutors no. <persName>Sam Smith [Samuel Wells Smith’49]</persName> was dean very, very helpful. But when I think about it I probably didn't communicate with him as much as some of the other brothers did. And so the insight and mental support that I could have received from him, I did not.  I was sort of in the middle, you know? just another brother walking, you know, it's my English Professor, I want to say was <persName>Professor King</persName>, but I don't remember now, but She was the person that really helped me with English and she was a sister, and I really probably need to look her name up but she was in one of my lowest times she provided support and help me. </u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Yeah, thanks for sharing that. Actually, <persName>Sam Smith</persName> is from <placeName>New Jersey</placeName> like me. yeah, I heard a lot about him and his work.</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">Yeah. If I remember, we put a bench up there. <persName>Sam Smith</persName> bench. So, yeah, I knew <persName>Sam</persName> but I didn't connect with him as much and maybe it's because I thought I didn't need to with that.   </u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Yeah I guess one last thing about the faculty in the school as a whole so when you came as a student there was a transition in administration in the college. So the president when you came in was <persName>John Sloan Dickey</persName> and moved from him being the president to <persName>Kemeny</persName> [John George Kemeny] if I am not wrong. So the transition made any difference in the way the college, Minister itself when or like nothing really changed. Did the administration kind of influence the interaction among Black students?     </u>
      <u who="MARABLE">Well yeah, it's all relative. Yes, it was another face, but, but the thoughts and concepts for inclusion, I would have to say, were different with <persName>Kemeny</persName>. So his daughter. And, my wife lived in the same dorm, and became good friends, which was the result of his conversion changing the whole student experience to this Dartmouth plan. This Dartmouth plan was structured and set up that allowed you to do things and create programs that would serve the student's best interest as far as I'm concerned, so talk about students and I'll talk about as best, I can about the faculty. So the Dartmouth plan came along, it allowed me to manage, going to school, and not going to school and working during the term in my mind, Which would be a term that most people go to school. So I ended up working in a bank in <placeName>New Jersey</placeName>. Some <orgName>Elizabeth Trust Company</orgName> under the start of the d plan. I learned a little bit more about business and, sort of refined the direction I was going to go business. So I doubt I would have had that opportunity. if the only time to work in a situation like that was during the summer, you know, so in my mind thought process, this allowed you to expand your opportunity for as work goes. That Dartmouth plan just allowed for overall flexibility, to take the students. the Dartmouth plan. Also, ultimately resulted in me meeting with my wife of 46 years. So in my sophomore year they changed, they changed the whole makeup, they invited women to be fully matriculated, students. And so, yeah, I mean, I don't know if <persName>Dicky</persName> would have wanted that but <persName>Kemeny</persName> wanted that.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">You brought up another point that  I wanted to ask about you were in the middle of great change being that Title Nine passed in <date when='1972'>1972</date>. And like you mentioned, women were able to finally come to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. Your wife was one of the first Black women and a member of one of the few classes of Black women who actually graduated from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> which is like history. Could you tell me a little about how you met her and what was her experience like? As much as you know. Did she experience some of the things you experience or was it different for her?    </u>
      <u who="MARABLE">So the initial premise to go to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> for me was that  I needed a school that had no women and after that a couple of weeks I realized that really wasn't necessarily a good idea. So, in the class of 76, when my wife came, It was hand-to-hand combat. I mean yeah there I think they might have been 10 15, 20 sisters. There were not that many. So her experience was not necessarily very good. I mean, every brother thought he had a line. Yeah, you know. She had a lot of proposals from different guys.so we met in the bookstore. So as a freshman year, you're following the rules. You go to the bookstore. Most of your books are down in the basement. You see this long line so you get well. Get in the line. In the second year, you realize they're about five registers on the second floor. And if you just walk up to one of the registers that's empty you don't have to wait this long line but as a freshman, you are in the long line. So I was looking for some books. And she was in it in the distance, her back was turned to me. and I guess she was looking at some books and she just felt me staring at her and she turned around and smile I get her to follow me, basically I told her that I  know the shortline and so she decided she wanted to go on the shortline. And after that, we talked and we spent the day together. At that time, I had a car and so I show her a little bit around the campus. And then spent some good years on campus there.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">so let me see. So your sophomore at this point? Could you tell me about <orgName>greek life</orgName>? It had had any influence on you?                 ,</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">You know, it was an interest. As I was navigating and finding a level of friends. After freshman year during freshman year you know they sort of did this Rush thing. Now I was around some of the guys and went to  Kappa, <orgName>Sigma Nu</orgName> because the guys that were on, my floor, were members. So they invite me in and has plenty of beer on the floor. And, you know, people would take a couple of steps and slide on the beer-covered floor. So I'm not going to say I didn't do some of that stuff. I did but it wasn't something I did all the time because, you know, it just didn't seem to be a good use of time. They get blithering drunk on the weekend. but <orgName>Greek life</orgName> was not instrumental in forming the environment for me.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Thank you for sharing. I know <orgName>greek Life</orgName> is such a big thing at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> so I needed to ask about that. Do you go to do any study abroad or it was not something that interested you?</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">Yeah. Well, so the term in The D plan when <persName>Kennedy</persName> came in created that it allowed me to go to <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and learn how to speak Spanish, great, great time, right? I lived with a family road down the liver, the former which is the major. So, my mind is like Broadway but it's the reformer who Jumped on the buses like everybody else hanging on the outside of the bus. And it was an excellent opportunity to learn Spanish interestingly. I would be able to socialize and be with people but I guess to a Great extent. I was a loner. Yeah, I  play cards. You know, I didn't hang out with others that much. so I went to <placeName>Veracruz</placeName> with a group of other people. We went to different places together it was fun. Met some people there and had some very unique experiences in <placeName>Veracruz</placeName>. But yeah, the language study abroad program is very, very good., my daughter, did the LSA.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Do you feel like you had any kind of connection with studying abroad? Like the influence of people to get more students to get involved with like for example the D plan and these new policies because studying abroad was only implementable when <persName>Kemeny</persName> came to office. So do you feel like there was more special attention to other students getting involved with those policies?  do you feel like there was no preference and everybody was thought to be the same?</u>
      <u who="Marable">So, I'm going to answer the question and if I don't answer it in the way that you asked it, then say it again. So I don't think at least I didn't feel any pressure or focus on any group of students to take advantage of the D plan. And I think that the college itself allowed people to sit back and think of what they wanted to do. And so for me, you know, when I looked at the course requirements and when I had to do going away and to <placeName>Mexico</placeName> can to fulfill that language requirement and then coming back and working In the winter when everybody else was in school worked well for me to to fill that language requirement and then still get some work experience because economics and psychology as a major really really didn't Focus directly for business. At least what I thought business was now because of the way that the system was I don't know if some of the other Black students had different counseling. </u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Yeah, there is a little noise in the background. I think they just passing by. Let's keep go  </u>
      <u who="MARABLE">So the D plan, so normally people would take a certain group of credit courses and so the d  plan basically increases The number of quarters or semesters one. All right. And it and it allowed you to mix and match how many you actually had to be on one campus versus Off campus. And then I think it also had adjusted only time adjustments with the grade point average. So it was a lot of, a lot of things that occurred from. I want to say four semesters to six semesters that you basically had to engage.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO"><name type="event">The Vietnam War</name> had any, you know any like influence in your studies and overall social environment in <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. </u>
      <u who="Marable">so the relationship of <name type="event">Vietnam</name> was present all the time but it was winding down. And so because of I guess where I live and the fact that I didn't personally know of people going to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>. I knew guys who were concerned about the draft numbers. So there was a concern, but I didn't really know any guys, very close, who went to <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> to fight. There was a draft and so, you know, they did it. Still the number of days and if your draft number was low and I, my definition of low was under 200. You had a better than 50% chance of getting drafted. So as it turned out, my number was like, in the 300 and so, you know, I was good. I, you know, I had no need or reason to be concerned about the draft at 300, but  I want to say from afar, I know guys who effectively joined <orgName>ROTC</orgName> to, sort of avoid the different situation, personally, it didn't have the greatest impact, probably as it should have, but that had a lot to do with the number that I received in the draft.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">All right. I don't recall any other big world events going on. There was any kind of like influence in terms of condemnation from part of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> students like being anti-war and rising up to protest or any kind of strong opinions from students about the war.</u>
      <u who="Marable">so, so there was a Just the couple years before I arrived in the 70s, it was, there was a lot of turmoil. There was a lot of strife in it, in the latter 60s. And so it's I almost want to say, After, the brothers shook things up during that period in time, it was like the college said, okay, whatever you want to do. We're going to do it and things took a break. I don't, I don't remember any, any college protest. I think. things didn't turn back around until the 80s, you know when Some white folks felt entitled to do things but yeah.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">So I haven't asked you about the <orgName>Afro-American society</orgName> yet. Something really important. You know, many, many students spent a bunch of time, a bunch of efforts to make it happen, created. And to increase the number of Black students to give them a voice for them to have a safe space. Would you tell me a little bit about your connection with society? The connection and impact they had on your campus experience and could you tell me about the impact that you think the society had on campus? If you think it had any. because I can only read it but you were actually there.</u>
      <u who="Marable">I would say I'm forever grateful for the vision of some of the brothers, you know, who are in the 60s and 70s who recognized the need for the creation of a safe space for Black people. It was through their efforts that were obtained. It was through their efforts that it was created. And it was as far as I was concerned I don't think that this school experience would be what it is for most Black people without society. Now, if it wasn't for those individuals who stood up and persuaded the people that needed to be persuaded that there was a need to create a safe space that, you know, there are cultural differences and that space would provide an opportunity. Need for people of color to recharge. when I was a student, I don't think I realized that need. I think I realize it more now but when I was a student I don't think I realized it. I just knew that. What I had to do and will continue to do is to be, hopefully, part of the solution. So if there's a call for, some Black people there. I'm gonna be there. If there's an event that's taking place at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. I want to go because I don't want them to get confused that there were no Black people around which, which has a lot to do with it. I am on the <orgName>Dartmouth New York City executive committee</orgName>, which has things to do with my class representation. I know when I was a student, my involvement probably wasn't as much as it could have been or should have been but now, you know, I'll let it be known that I was a brother of Black people. <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> scarred a lot of people. you know, the experience when my wife and I did 25th reunions we had talked to people who had not been back for 20 years and they were having a physical reaction that which when you think about it in hindsight you ask, what happened? What happened to somebody that when they think about going back to some place they feel ill? You know. So your question is vital we as a student when Dasa had parties we were there and it was you know it was like sort of coming back home you know. I don't think I needed that maybe I did, but I didn't realize I needed it. So I think society has to stay. I think it provides a safe space for students and you look around you. We are all under attack. We're all under attack, you can't hide. If you walk out, someone sees.  Whether directly or indirectly society provides a safe space for people who need to be recharged and rejuvenated.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Thanks for sharing That. Something that I wanted to ask about once you're already approaching your senior year, you told me you were thinking about business so you major in economics. So could you tell me how I was <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> supported you in getting yourself that first job after college and do you find a lot of support from the African American community in any way to do that? </u>
      <u who="Marable">I think the one thing that <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> does in terms of providing support, is that the Mystique of graduating from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> generally always opens doors. And so, so that process I believe I was able to take advantage. And so people assume a certain level of intelligence expert and certain level or ability to do things that other individuals might not be able to do so it did help in that sense? Yes, it did. Did I go to any white alumni? No. Did I go to any Black alumni for help? I didn't know very many Black alumni when I graduated because I  wasn't connected. I didn't know who to go to anyway. All right. It's so the career services had a very loose type of Database or directory of alumni? Yeah, I don't think I was directed or knew of any Black alumni who at that time were in a position to help somebody like me in the areas that I was focused on. The willingness and ability to work hard. The ability to write effectively and reasonably well while thinking critically were the things that I would take away from my <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> experience and help. </u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Great. You currently work in <orgName>Prudential</orgName>, could you tell me how you hold positions in other companies before that and how were switched from job titles and different companies? After you finish Dartrmtouh. Did your experience at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> influence the way that you decided to direct your career if have any influence at all? And yeah, could you please talk to me a little bit about what is your current job title and what you do today?</u>
      <u who="Marable">So currently, I do work for <orgName>Prudential</orgName>, I'm a financial advisor. Planner and basically, what I do is help people keep more of the money, more of the money that they make. So I talk about budgeting and talk about insurance and talk about investing. About what you need for retirement planning. And I talk about estate planning in those three areas basically. Provide an opportunity to create a holistic picture of an individual so that they manage their Financial Resources better. So when I graduated from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, didn't know what I wanted to do and I had banking internship experience. So I decided that going to banking would give me more of a Sensor on how I would attack the business world. so I interviews probably five, six, seven, eight, nine, 10, 11, and 12 interviews, got nine invitations to join Banks and so I didn't know the difference between Banks, Trust, <orgName>Citibank</orgName>, and <orgName>Chase</orgName>. They were all the same. Now, why did I get all those acceptances? I'm gonna count that on <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, the gut, the recruiters come up to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. You, sit down interview and talk to them. I could sit down and talk to somebody. There's something is if this guy graduated from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, he's got to know how to do a certain series of things that's the door opening. So my choice of <orgName>Chase</orgName> was based solely on. Who is paying the most money Okay manufacturers Hanovers might have been a better fit for me but <orgName>Chase</orgName>, paid $20 more so that's where I work. From that experience, with <orgName>Chase</orgName>, I got involved more with a different life than college. So, when I graduated to the real world, I got real-world responses that Black folk get from white folk. which I didn't necessarily have to deal with in <placeName>Hanover</placeName>. But from <orgName>Chase</orgName>, I stayed there, for several years, then decided it might be interesting to join <orgName>the Federal Reserve Bank</orgName>. So after <orgName>chase</orgName>, I work for the chair of the <orgName>Federal Reserve Bank</orgName> as a bank examiner. So I would go around analyzing auditing banks that were in the second federal district and I stayed there for several years and decided that it would be a good good thing to move to a different environment. So every time you move from one job to another, you get a 20% increase. You know in hindsight, it was a good money move but very poor for retirement planning. So every time I moved to a new company the clock would start at 0. So the five years from another place. Didn't count for the new place. And so I lost. I lost 10, or 15 years of retirement accumulated credit that I would have received if I had stayed in one place. So, so from the <orgName>Federal Reserve Bank</orgName>, you know, then I realized that I needed to stay closer to home Joan. And I am thinking about a family. So I started working for this insurance company. Ss their audit manager and I stayed there for a few years and realize that my way of doing business was different than the person that I reported. And so I left them and eventually ended up at <orgName>Goldman Sachs</orgName>. So <orgName>Goldman Sachs Investment Bank</orgName> and I were part of the investment banking division, provided the background support with my Excel skills there, and stay there for a while. Then after I decided, to move again I ended up working for a company, very similar to <orgName>Prudential</orgName> which was called accent. Now, it's called <orgName>Equitable</orgName> and stayed there for several years. And in <date when='2017'>2017</date> moved to <orgName>Prudential</orgName>, which is where I am now. So you know what?  <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> helps me in getting my first job technically.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">I was wondering because you mention your wife. So at this point, you were still with your wife. She will have graduated from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> class of 76. Do you guys stay through all those transitions? and also could you mention how you got involved in the <orgName>New York club of Dartmouth</orgName>?</u>
      <u who="Marable">so, As it relates to my wife. My junior year we married and so that's <date when='1972'>72</date> so since then we have been together, So I'm not going to say maybe that's the reason why I didn't hang out the <orgName>am</orgName> and you know, do all other stuff. But since <date when='1972'>72</date> we've been together so that togetherness is through the studies at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> through the different jobs that I've had we got married in <date when='1975'>1975</date>. Also she, so let me tell you about this lady here. She did private school completely differently than this public school kid. Well, well-educated very much, a critical thinker relaxing, very much off. She started to get school. Premed. Um, you took a good chunk of those classes. She graduated in <date when='1976'>76</date> but finished her coursework and <date when='1975'>75</date>. Okay. So, we talked about the Dartmouth plan Dartmouth plan allowed you to accelerate your program and finish your requirements early. And so, that's what she did. So that's you know, that's it's no small. It takes a lot of focus and skill, she could she graduated early, and she walked with her class but was done. Nineteen seventy-seventy-five.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">So yeah. Just to rephrase. I was asking you how that transition was. Like when you were trying to formulate your family, how were all those job transitions challenging? were easy? to make and also your involvement with the <orgName>Dartmouth New York club</orgName>. </u>
      <u who="Marable">So, so, my wife's family, Jones, family is a very close family. My parents were married for 60 years, So, my family. My parents separated and so everything was sort of disjointed. So, in the back of my mind, I did not want to put any children through the kind of stuff that I went through. So it is So, we were married, eight years before I felt comfortable enough to think about having kids and so when I had this job, that was keeping me on the road we started to think about children. That's when I changed jobs to one where I did not have to travel as much. So we agreed that I would do the work outside and she would do the work inside, which meant she would take care of the kids we thought would be appropriate. So with that in mind, We managed to generate enough income to buy a house, a brownstone in <placeName>Brooklyn</placeName>. Which was going to be the place where we ultimately end up raising both of our children. All right. So I was working she was staying at home. And continued my engagement with <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>  So when I, graduated and I was part of the <orgName>alumni Council</orgName>. Because I guess felt the need to give back. You know, also to make sure everybody knew that Black people went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> because a lot of people didn't want to come back there. You know the experience was so raw when they left that was it. So my experience was you know it's just another. I went back to the <orgName>alumni Council</orgName>. You know, I don't recall how I got connected to the <orgName>Dartmouth Club</orgName>. I'm not a <orgName>Dartmouth Club</orgName> member but I am part of the <orgName>Dartmouth executive committee of New York City</orgName>. It's a little bit different I don't go to the swimming pool and use a hotel, you know, like in the <orgName>Yale Club</orgName>, I am just part of the <orgName>executive committee</orgName> and so that engagement has lasted <date>more than 10 years</date>, okay? <persName>Joan</persName> doesn't get involved with that, I do it just to stay connected and business. and then at some point, I became the director of the regional director of <orgName>Bada</orgName>, you know? I don't want to mess up what <orgName>Bada</orgName> means. <orgName>Black Association of black alumni</orgName>. That's what <orgName>Bada</orgName> means and I did it because what I knew was that they were a lot of Black alumni in the <placeName>New York</placeName>, <placeName>New Jersey</placeName>, and <placeName>Connecticut</placeName> area, which was All scattered then. I didn't know a lot of alumni, that's not the case now, it's better. But so I will say that the connection with <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> It is as relates to the club was there because I felt there was a need to have that connection. The connection with <orgName>Bada</orgName> is there because I felt it was needed to have that connection. The reason why <persName>Joan</persName> [Jaon Marable' 76] and I hosted the 25th Union Bada reunion was that there was a need and they were, you know, they were some people who likewise agreed with us, that there was a need.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">I have read in your bibliography that you have been part of some community outreach and community service?, could you tell me a little about it? </u>
      <u who="Marable">so I probably am going to Tribute giving back to my father and my mother in probably somewhere along the lines of engagement in church activities. My mother was, you know, part of the church Deacon. My father was like the captain of this <orgName>Salvation Army</orgName> bell. He lived in <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> at the time. So not that I can contribute <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> is having me think of philanthropic ideas or you know giving back I just would attribute that more to my blackness and experience of You know, growing up. So I guess now 24 years or so, my wife and I were trying to decide where to live. I wanted to live in <placeName>Westchester County</placeName> and she said she wasn't having that it was too small and too sleepy. So we moved to <placeName>Brooklyn</placeName> and so part of the moving to <placeName>Brooklyn</placeName>, I did not want my kids to go to public school, they would have to go to private-independent schools. So both of them ended up going to <orgName>Packer Collegiate Institute</orgName>, Independent School in <placeName>Brooklyn</placeName>. So the result of them going to an independent school. The result of going to the independent of going school. There was an organization that provided a safe space for young people to have periodic meetings, and talk about topics related to young people, particularly students of color. But the organization went defunct, they ran out of money. The people that were doing it, needed the money to live. So the staff of the organization say we lost the grant we are sorry, and this is the last meeting. And so this was an organization we consider very useful to help her daughter navigate life in this white institution, <orgName>Packer</orgName>, all right, and so she comes home crying, everybody's upset the way I remember the story is a little different than how <persName>Joan</persName> remembers the story, but the bottom line is as a team, we create this organization in conjunction with four students call <orgName>Dais</orgName> its acronym for <orgName>Diversity Awareness Initiative for students</orgName>. And so we did it and probably still do it because it's necessary. It's an unpaid job for my wife. That's necessary to keep it going we figure it out through <orgName>General Family Resources</orgName>. So it grew from maybe about 100 hundred kids In, we started. When I say back in <date when='1999'>1999</date> could be over the years. Prior to the pandemic, we would have about 500 kids come to our annual conference. We provided a safe space for students to talk about topics of being a teen and issues you know, that were concerning to people of color. And so it developed to the extent that almost all the independent schools have students have had students come to. Our programs would be twice a month, or students from <orgName>Collegian</orgName> to <orgName>Brearley</orgName> to <orgName>Horace Mann</orgName> to Polly <orgName>Polly prep</orgName>, all of the major independent schools, we have some of the protocol schools, some Public Schools, we accept anybody who wants to come over the last two years. We've been virtual, which has been sort of tough. But so in our last month of meeting, we talked about the topic of effectively how you deal with systemic racism that occurs in institutions of learning. And so it was a robust conversation. We teach kids facilitating School skills, we teach them how to develop and grow. And so, I don't know if you look at <orgName>CNN</orgName> at all, but even <persName>McCann</persName> is the sister that sort of she's covering <placeName>Georgia</placeName>. So she was a <orgName>Dais</orgName> member and you know when she was one of the independent schools. So so that's one of the things that I do to give back. currently, I am President of the <orgName>Lincoln Civic Block Association</orgName> that is in central <placeName>Brooklyn</placeName>, the <placeName>Crown Heights</placeName> area thinking about it wouldn't work first graph, our JCs.  I want to say and I probably shouldn't say, but I want to say it's a natural thing to do to give back where you can, how you can because invariably there was someone else who had given back something that had a positive impact. Yeah, so <orgName>Dais</orgName> is one of activity, and <orgName>Block Association</orgName> is another activity also currently I am a member I Define them as a major Chamber of Commerce, <orgName>Brooklyn Chamber of Commerce</orgName>, and the <orgName>Queen's chamber of Commerce</orgName>, and you know, participating in ribbon cuttings, and that kind of stuff. I am also involved with a local <orgName>Merchants Association</orgName> in <placeName>Queens</placeName>. And You know.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Yeah, thanks so much. That's a lot of work that you do and thanks for that and is really incredible. Do you find yourself that would you not be at, For example, a graduate of <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> or a person who went to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> will you still be doing all the same things that you do? Or do you feel that <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> was something fundamental for your decisions, after college? </u>
      <u who="MARABLE">That's an interesting question I can't answer that I really don't know. I don't know if I had gone to <orgName>Northwestern</orgName> where there I would have learned the same or similar skills that I learned at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. Yeah, when I graduated, when I was going to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>, I told myself, you know, I'm going to be the president of a major company. I'm president, it's not a Major company. And so, I don't know. I don't know if I'd gone to a state school. Whether where the experience academically would have been any different, I guess they're supposed to be, I guess, I know they should be so but, but for me, Whether it would have been different, I don't know, I don't know.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Well those are all the questions I have for today and like you answer so many so thank you so much for that. It was like a great pleasure and I know this interview will be used for future Black students who are just like us. And like you mentioned, understand what all the Black students from the same or different backgrounds went through in <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. The same things, I went through, and this interview will contribute to helping them. Thanks so much for your time. Do you have any final comments when you like to tell me?</u>
      <u who="MARABLE">I appreciate this opportunity to share my experience with those students who are sort of feel themselves to be in the middle. You know, we all were connected because of what we look like but our experience is maybe definitely different. Some people may have grown up in cities. Some people may have grown up in homes, but that was not the way you would envision a home. Parents are separated, and some people may have grown up having, to work just to provide food for themselves. Now some people grew up where all of the pleasures of life will provide for them because their parents are making a lot of money. But there is a middle and that's that is how I see my experience at <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. That's how I see myself now, if I was to go if I had a choice to you to do it again, to go to <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName>. Again, I would, I would probably experience even more or try to like the Freshman week trip that I didn't go on.them. I think that being a <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> student graduating from <orgName>Dartmouth</orgName> puts me in an Elite Class. And not many can claim that. Love it or hate it. I will recognize the fact that I did join that Elite Class of people. So that's what I like to say. And I want to thank you for being such an easy person with the questions and maybe when I get back to <placeName>Hanover</placeName> I look you up, I'll let you know, and we'll get together. Let's get together for ice cream. Something rather.</u>
      <u who="ROMANO">Yeah I'll be down I'll be down. Definitely thanks so much for your inspiring words.                </u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
